howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
unfortunately we had some technical
issues while recording this episode and
the sound quality isn't up to our
usual standards nonetheless it's very
listenable
and the content is great
today's guest is seth lloyd professor of
mechanical engineering at mit
and author of the book programming the
universe
hi seth great to have you on hi jim it's
great to be here yeah this is going to
be an interesting conversation talk
about
going from the microsphere to the
macrosphere and everything in between
the ridge programming universe when it
first came out quite a while ago
and i reread it for territory for this
episode and there's an
awful lot in that book we're not going
to cover everything from it
we're going to cover some of it we're
going to talk a fair amount about
what is quantum mechanics what is
quantum computing what's the state of
the art etc
so let's get started let's start with
some basics
how is the quantum world different from
the classical world
it's smaller and it's weirder
so the quantum mechanics describes how
things behave at their most fundamental
level
you know the level of atoms molecules
elementary particles
and the main thing to remember about it
is that things behave differently
and in a weird fancy strange way
so sometimes you know stay it's like
quantum mechanics is kind of the james
brown sciences
whatever's there it's got to be funky
[Laughter]
interesting yeah one of my long-term
hobbies actually
is reading in the field known as quantum
interpretation
i fell into this weird habit by reading
a book called quantum reality by a guy
named nick herbert
uh-huh with that book yeah absolutely
yeah and ever since i've sort of kept up
with the evolution of the field
and it is interesting to hear something
so fundamental
in our sciences and yet there's some
significant number like
five or ten different interpretations of
what
it all means and none of them are
inconsistent with the experimental
results
yet right including one of my favorite
you know again
for the shorthand of quantum mechanics
is
there's inherent randomness in you know
the positions the spins you know the
various things we measure
and yet there's still a school it seems
like maybe it's even
gaining strength at the moment that
quantum phenomena may not actually be
random it's just that we don't
understand the mechanisms well enough
maybe talk a little bit about quantum
interpretations and your views
on what's going on there
sure sure jim i thought that's a subject
dear to my heart because one of
the way i got into working on ideas of
information
and quantum mechanics came from doing a
master's in philosophy of science at
cambridge university studying
foundations of quantum mechanics and
quantum interpretations
so i share your interest in it and
you're right there
are at least 10 different
interpretations out there
and the interesting thing about them is
they're all consistent with experiment
as you say
and all of them are each one in its own
way is deeply
unsatisfactory if any one of them
were completely satisfactory then
there'd be only one interpretation
but none of them are satisfactory and i
interpret this
to mean that really it's hard to come up
with a good interpretation of quantum
mechanics
in fact my belief is that we will never
have an interpretation of quantum
mechanics that satisfies
ordinary human beings or smart human
beings or philosophers of science
simply because quantum mechanics is so
strange and counterintuitive
that there's no way to interpret that
strangeness and counterintuitiveness
away
yeah that's certainly one of the meta
theories right but it's just
shut up and calculate basically we'll
never understand it
uh no no i'm not i'm not advocating that
i think we should think about it but we
should be aware that we're not likely to
get a good solution
i mean the basic problem is that as you
mentioned there's a
tension between determinism and
uh indeterminism or chancy probabilistic
behavior
that the schrodinger equation and
equations of motion that govern quantum
mechanics are themselves deterministic
so you set them running you say here's
the situation now
what's going to happen in the future and
then the equations just churn on ahead
and they say here's the state of the
system in the future
completely determined by the state in
the past but
when you actually look at the
predictions for the results of
experiments
and you look at what you observe then
you find that those predictions
are probabilistic and not determined so
how do you reconcile those two features
the fact that the underlying theory is
in some sense deterministic and yet it
makes
probabilistic predictions for what's
going to happen that's pretty tough
interesting
now do you have a view do you have a an
intuition shall we say on this
randomness versus determinism question
or is it just so damn hazy
it's not worth speculating in your view
oh no i do i actually i have a
view which i find reasonably satisfying
i say no no views are satisfied
are you know perfectly satisfying but as
you know well from
reading about this that the the kind of
original interpretation that people came
up with came
largely from neil's wars called the
copenhagen interpretation
and bohr said okay the underlying laws
are deterministic
um but these just describe kind of
microscopic phenomenon when you get to
macroscopic things
like measurement devices that are making
measurements then
these are you know kind of categorically
different than the microscopic devices
so their behaviors can be different
and that's pretty annoying because like
well you know the devices are made up
you know our measurement apparatus
is made up of of atoms and molecules and
things behaving
according to laws of quantum mechanics
why shouldn't they also obey the laws of
quantum mechanics
so that's one interpretation and then
another
very commonly used interpretation which
is pretty wacky but is
is adopted by many people is called the
many worlds interpretation
which says yeah the underlying laws are
deterministic
and so you set this up and the universe
evolves in a deterministic fashion
but every time you make a measurement
or look at something happening that
appears to be probabilistic
the universe splits into two pieces uh
and you only get one of them and which
one you get is determined by the laws of
chance so it's probabilistic
and that's made okay that explains
what's going on as you say
it fits what the what we see
experimentally but then you have the
every time you make a measurement this
whole other piece of the universe just
split off and you're never going to see
it again
and um it constitutes you know another
world different from our world
that's also not very satisfactory yep
it's crazy in fact i had a very intense
conversation with murray gelman one day
when i was out
santa fe institute started at lunch and
then we ended up walking down to his
office and talking for about two hours
and we went all around these various
theories and he finally
used some words which i found that he
probably hasn't used with anybody else
since i've found anybody else that says
they ever heard these words from them
he said you know jim here's one way to
think about it which is
take the many worlds interpretation do
the math
as if many worlds but by some mechanism
we don't understand
only one of those worlds is actually
realized and the rest just don't happen
he said that's kind of a layman's way to
describe his own views
on quantum interpretation what do you
think of that
yeah no i i agree with that well you
know i did my first post talk with
murray and we spent a lot of time
working on what's called the coherent
histories formulation of quantum
mechanics
which can be thought of as a a kind of a
a version of many worlds but instead of
just looking at the world now to say we
split up into these different worlds we
look at the whole history
of the universe past and future and so
then
we have one past history but our history
can branch off into many other histories
in the future
um marie and i were pretty much on the
same page about this
so i i actually agree with that and i
have a modest
and mild proposal about interpretation
here i think that
a lot of the the problem that people
have particularly physicists about this
is that
the issue about many worlds is it's very
hard to believe
in the the existence of these other
worlds in which everything
is radically different from the way it
is in our world i mean
are they real or are they not we have
our world
about which we have empirical evidence
you know if that's the case i had a
delicious bowl of oatmeal
with homemade rhubarb compote
this morning and in another world i had
a delicious fried egg
but i'm in this world right so i know
that i have information about this world
of things are the case
so what distinguishes our world from
these other worlds
is we have evidence about what is the
case in our world
oh i like to think of this in the
following and this is you know
physicists don't like this in general
but philosophers are okay
it's like physicists want to believe
there's only one thing that's real
and if it's there in the wave function
of the universe by god it's real
the problem with that with many worlds
is that you've got all these other
worlds that are by definition real
because
if you declare them to be so so my
my simple solution to this uh which of
course will not you know many people
won't like if that's okay
is that really there are we should
distinguish between empirical reality
things that we know to be the case
because we have evidence that they're
the case
and then this kind of wave function
reality being real in the wave function
of the universe
because the wave function of the
universe contains all these other worlds
where things are by definition different
empirically different from the way they
are
in our world and so there are different
things we have our world that we see
we know it to be the case and that's one
piece of the whole wave function of the
universe and then the wave function
contains all these other worlds
which are real in a wave function kind
of way but not in an empirical fashion
and that for me is good enough
interesting that's a kind of interesting
fudge i'd try to get my head around that
later
it's not a fudge it's i'm simply saying
that
that physicists want to say there's only
one kind of reality right but
saying i'm saying okay there's reality
is it just in the wave function
and then there's what was empirical
reality which refers to one part of the
wave function
i'm not fudging i'm just being precise
okay i'll retract fudge and say hmm
that's yet another
interpretation i'm going to try to get
my head around it later
let's talk about another phenomenon
which will turn out to be extremely
important as we dive into quantum
computing which is
entanglement non-locality can you talk
about that a little bit
absolutely yeah entanglement is one of
those james brown
features i was at a james brown concert
long ago and somebody
james brown finished a song and then
somebody else somebody said james what
are you going to play next
and he said i don't know but whatever it
is it's got to be funky
so as i said quantum mechanics is a
james brown of sciences it's very funky
and entanglement is kind of the funkiest
central funkitude
of quantum mechanics so so entanglement
is a very funny feature well finally i
don't know about in the haha sense but
strange and counterintuitive feature of
quantum mechanics
where things can be correlated with each
other or have information
about each other and they have strictly
more information than you're allowed to
have
classically and it shows up in ways if
you have
an entangled pair of particles and said
let's say we have
we have two electrons and they have spin
and you can say
one is spinning clockwise the other is
spinning counterclockwise
they can be in a situation where if you
look at each electron
on its own its spin clockwise or
counterclockwise is completely not
determined
so if you measure it then you say hey
are you spinning clockwise or
counterclockwise
it will say you know in a chance fashion
it will say oh i'm spinning clockwise
then if you measure the other electron
you'll find that the spin is always
anti-correlated so it's in the opposite
way so if the first electron is spinning
clockwise the second one is spinning
counterclockwise
or if you measure the first one you find
it's spinning counterclockwise you find
second one is spinning clockwise now
what's weird about this
is that until you actually make the
measurement then
the electron is neither clockwise
spinning clockwise
nor counterclockwise it's spinning both
clockwise and counterclockwise at the
same time
in some weird and funky quantum
mechanical fashion that nobody has a
good intuition for
and so when you measure the first
electron it has to as as
it were declare itself to say oh i'm
clockwise
but as soon as it declares itself to be
clockwise you know that if you were to
go and measure the other electron you'd
find it's counterclockwise
so there's some weird sense in this
entanglement
as it's called that these two electrons
are in an indeterminate
but anti-correlated state and somehow if
you make a measurement
on one kind of thereby making that
electron declare itself to be in a
determined state
let's say clockwise then at the same
instant
the other electron you know has declared
itself to be counterclockwise
and this is weird and strange and
einstein called this
spooky action at a distance actually he
called it in german
which sounds more impressive
and for many years people thought oh my
goodness this is terrible would it allow
instantaneous communication from one
electron to another
though as it turns out it doesn't allow
communications it's merely some funny
way in which the two electrons are more
intimate with each other
interesting yeah in fact people are
interested in this your book actually
does the best job i've ever seen
explaining why you can't cheat and use
entanglement to send information over a
distance
that's the easy fallacy to say looks
like faster than speed of light suppose
we had
two electrons that were separated one
went to alpha centauri one state on
earth
you did a measure on alpha centauri we
could tell here on earth some
information your book does a great job
explaining how that can't happen mother
nature just does not seem to want us to
act it's be the light
i believe this to be a good thing not
just a good thing it's the law
right if we talk later on about
about time travel i can qualify that
statement
oh dude we may not get there we'll say
now closely related to entanglement
is the concept of coherence probably
both actually rooted in the deeper idea
of superposition
talk a little bit about coherence and
how that's similar to and related to
a little different at least from a point
of view perspective from entangled
again that's going to be important as we
talk about quantum computing
yeah so i indeed so coherence
is well coherence when referring to
human beings mean that they're making a
coherent case for what they're doing
and uh i'm i'm not going to claim that
i'm going to be coherent talking about
coherence but i'll give it a shot
so in quantum mechanics the notion of
coherence comes from
this feature that when quantum mechanics
was
first formalized by schrodinger and
heisenberg in the 1920s
it was about waves so schrodinger came
up with this wave equation which
said oh look you know each situation
each wave for instance electron spinning
clockwise or counterclockwise
corresponds to a wave and if you think
of waves of water or waves of sound you
know
waves of water or the surface of the
water
wiggling up and down in a periodic and
regular fashion
and so waves have a notion of coherence
in the sense that
if you think of a water wave that's
going undulating up and down
it's got a regular wave undulating up
and down and when you have two waves
that that collide with each other
they can interfere and the parts where
the waves
are both high become extra high the
parts where the waves are both low
become extra low
and the parts where one wave is high and
the other wave is low
then cancel each other out so the waves
interfere with each other in a way
that's coherent that's how it's
described and all it really means is
that the amplitude of the waves how high
or low they are
just add up together in a regular and
coherent fashion so
coherence in quantum mechanics refers to
this wave-like nature
of quantum mechanics and the notion of
superposition that you mentioned before
simply means that when you take two wave
corresponding to two possible states
you just add them together and the
resulting wave is the sum of the two
waves
so mathematically and actually even you
know intuitively
and visualizing it that's what's going
on so you you have
states or waves coherence means that the
waves can add up in a systematic fashion
and superposition means
that if you withdraw a few waves then
uh you just add them together so that
actually doesn't sound so bad
the problem is when you try to relate it
to behavior of things like
electrons and and then square that with
your macroscopic intuition
so for example you know in quantum
mechanics the the amplitude of the wave
is related to where you're likely to
find a particle so if i have the wave
corresponding electron
and the wave is really big over here
then
that means if i make a measurement to
say where is the electron then it's
going to be likely to be over here
or if the wave is really big over there
and i measure to see where the electron
is then i'm likely to find the electron
over there
well that doesn't sound so bad it's okay
it has something to do with these
probabilities of measurement
but the problem is because of this
principle superposition
in quantum mechanics if you have two
waves then not only can you add them up
if you add them up the sum of these two
waves is a perfectly reasonable state
for the electron
so you know the wave electron
over here okay wave with the electron
over there
that's fine but when you add them up you
have a wave where there's a big
amplitude
for the electron being over here and a
big amplitude for the electron being
over there
and what does that mean well means that
in some funky quantum mechanical sense
the electron is here
and there at the same time and that's
pretty tough for
our feeble macroscopic minds to grasp
indeed and now let's make the turn
towards quantum computing because we've
set the foundations is this funky
concept that the electron or the photon
or whatever it is can be many things at
once
you know how do we use that to produce
quantum computing
and how is it fundamentally different to
classical computing
two big questions so feel free to take a
while to answer those two
ah well jim since you set it up pretty
well i think we are in good shape to
look at that because
really the basic distance between
quantum computing and classical
computing is what we were just talking
about
that is quantum computers are just
ordinary computers you've got bits of
information
you code information and bits you flip
the bits in a systematic fashion
and then you perform a computation you
process the information that's what
classical digital computers do
that's what quantum computers do but
because quantum
computers have access to this quantum
funkiness
then what they have is something more
than what classical computers have
in particular let's think of this
electron actually you know in a
classical computer the way you store a
bit of
information is you've got a whole bunch
of electrons you know you put the
electrons onto a capacitor you put them
over here
and you call that you know zero you take
to put them over there you put them on
another capacitor you call that
one okay and when you flip the bit you
say oh let's move the electrons
open a switch and let the electrons flow
from this capacitor to this other
capacitor
capacitor is just like a bucket for
electrons you toss electrons in the
bucket
and then flipping a bit in a computer is
like oh let's take the electrons from
this bucket and we'll empty it into that
other bucket so we take it from the zero
bucket we pop them into one bucket
okay fine and then you know the the the
way that
classical computers work is just simply
doing this in a systematic fashion let's
say
oh let's empty this bucket if this other
bucket is full and then let's fill up
this other bucket if the other bucket is
empty
and then let's do this many many many
many many times and that's what digital
computers are doing
okay what about a quantum computer well
quantum computer is like a classical
computer but
let's say we're storing a bit of
information on a single electron
so electron over here you know with its
wave
concentrated over here okay we'll call
that zero
electron over there this wave
concentrated over there
we'll call that one but then
electron with its wave over here and
over there
that's an electron that's here and there
at the same time that's a
a bit a quantum bit or a cubit
which is both zero and one at the same
time
again in some funky counter-intuitive
quantum sense which nobody really
understands
and that's at bottom the only difference
between
quantum computers and classical
computers is that quantum computers
quantum bits can be zero and one at the
same time
by taking advantage of this quantum
funkiness
it turns out to have a huge difference
in the capabilities
of computation right i mean the fact
that we can in some sense
explore all possible solutions more or
less simultaneously
at least for some algorithms give an
unbelievable
boost in their capability for instance
the first
time i ever heard of quantum computing
was shore's algorithm
and believe it or not there was probably
15 minutes when i actually understood
shore's algorithm and worked through it
enough
to really understood how it worked and i
go holy
did you maybe run through a little bit
how a relatively small
quantum computer could do what seems
impossible which is to
factor huge numbers how does
entanglement
allow that to happen yeah absolutely
we're just talking about how in a
quantum computer a quantum bit can be
zero and one at the same time
and then two quantum bits can be you
know they don't have to be either you
know zero one or one
zero they can be zero one and one zero
at the same time
they can be in the quantum superposition
of the two states zero
one and one zero and when they're in
this state then they're in this
entangled state
because if i measure the first one i
find the answer is zero then i know the
second one is in the state one
if i find the first one in the state one
i know the second one is in the state
zero
so this this principle of superposition
that a quantum bit or cubic can be zero
and one at the same time
when you apply it to two or more qubits
you get entangled states
and this is key for uh using quantum
computers to solve hard problems
a good way to think of this is the
problem but remember that the state of a
quantum system corresponds to a wave to
a solution to the schrodinger equation
and a classical computation all the bits
at any given time
have have a well-defined value
so you know each one is either zero or
one
but not zero and one at the same time
and you know so all the bits in the
classical computer at one point they're
like 0 one one zero one
one one zero for a small classical
computer but in aquatic computer
the bits can be zero one one one zero
zero one one zero
and one zero one zero one zero one zero
one zero one zero one
at the same time again it's hard to
understand how that works
in our intuitions but it's just a
superposition of two waves
so a nice way of thinking about this
this is a metaphor but it's very precise
metaphor because it actually has to do
with waves
is that a classical computation which is
a sequence
of states of bits is so like something
like you know
gregorian plane chant like
where there's only one sound there's no
harmony it's just a melody
one sound at each point whereas a
quantum computation
is the superposition of many sounds
simultaneously it's a symphony
everybody's playing it once and if they
play at once in a harmonious fashion
you can make a sound that you could
never obtain or even know what it
sounded like
if you just had a single cat with a
single note
so as i say this is a metaphor but it's
a good metaphor to keep in mind
so what happens for solving hard
problems like schwarz algorithm
so in 1994 my colleague peter shore
showed that
if you had a quantum computer you could
use this
symphonic nature of quantum computation
to solve a problem of considerable
practical interest
which is uh code breaking and he showed
you could use quantum computers to break
the commonly used public key
cryptosystems that we use whenever we
you know buy something over the internet
we buy something over the internet
you know i i i say to amazon i'd like to
buy these tea bags please
and they say okay send us your credit
card number
and i would say well i'm not going to
send my credit card number openly over
the internet they say that's fine we're
going to send you a public key
and you're going to use that to send us
your credit card number and once you've
combined your credit card number with a
public key nobody will know what your
credit card number is
but will be able to decode it using our
private key when you send it to us and i
say okay that's fine i really want my t
and this sounds good so you do that and
this is very useful as you can imagine
and uh this is what happens with all
these transactions over the internet
that whenever you want to send private
information
the retailer sends you a public key
which you use to encrypt your
information in a way that nobody else
can encrypt can
so that nobody else can discover it so
sure showed that by
uh being able to do something called
factoring
to take find a number and get given a
number which is the product of two large
numbers to find the other
two large numbers which when multiplied
together make the first number
so you're given r which is the product
of p and q
and given r you want to find p and q
that's the factoring problem like you
know
like 15 given 15 it's like
oh 15 is 3 times 5. so
um so when the numbers get very very big
this is a very hard problem and short
short showed how to do this the way that
he he showed how to do this
is related intimately with the wave like
nature of how
information is represented in quantum
mechanics
so if you have a wave like a wave in the
ocean
then the wave can have different
wavelengths and different periods
so when the waves are small the
wavelength is short
and the waves wiggle up and down very
rapidly when the waves are big the
wavelength is longer
and the waves are wiggling up and down
more slowly
so shor showed how to encode
the answer to this hard problem
of factoring and code breaking into a
huge long wave that stretches over
if you were to actually stretch it out
in space it would be larger than the
length of the universe
but if you can stretch it out you can
kind of curl it up into the quantum bits
of a quantum computer
and you want to find the period of this
wave you want to find
how fast it's wiggling up and down
and classically this is very hard to do
but quantum mechanically because quantum
mechanics is all about
waves it turns out that it's quite
possible in a straightforward fashion if
you're given a huge long wave and you
want to find out how fast it's wiggling
up and down
you can do that very efficiently and
straightforwardly on a quantum computer
it's a it's because quantum mechanics is
about waves
to begin with so shore took this
wave-like nature
of quantum mechanics showed how you
could encode the answer the solution to
a hard problem by finding
the wavelength of a long periodic wave
and then showed how you could use a
quantum computer to find that wavelength
and thereby factoring the numbers and
breaking the code
it's a very very very beautiful piece of
work and
it shows intimately how quantum
mechanics actually works because it
takes this very important feature of
quantum mechanics this wave-like feature
ordinary bits don't have but quantum
bits qubits do have
and then shows that how to elegantly
solve a hard problem
yeah that's an interesting as i said i
understood it for about 15 minutes and
here's an interesting personal
story shore's algorithm was actually
central to a key decision i made in my
life how about that who would have
thought it right in 2000 i had an
opportunity to sell
my internet company to verisign the
company that ran the digital certificate
business
which was based on the rsa crypto
algorithm that you just described
at that time essentially all the digital
certificates that did what you described
which would secure the transmission over
the web of your credit card to
amazon were sold by verizon they had a
quasi monopoly with one small competitor
they eventually bought them out
anyway they wanted to buy my company so
one of the things i had to do as part of
the due diligence
we were a publicly traded company so we
had to you know be
quite public about all our due diligence
was estimate what is the chances
in some reasonable period of time that
shore's algorithm will get implemented
in a quantum computer and break rsa
right we literally had to do that right
and i
you know again this was 2000 so nobody
had any clue really about how
fast quantum computing would progress
but we talked to some people and i would
say in classic american short-term
business thinking
we concluded that there was essentially
no chance it would happen in the next
five years
so we went ahead and did the deal and
then interestingly
after we did the deal i ended up running
the digital certificate business how
about that
so i literally had to worry about a
little bit
convinced myself i didn't have to worry
about it anytime soon which is a good
pivot actually
to the shores algorithm and many other
algorithms
in theory are exceedingly powerful
however
to get that power there has to be a size
of
entanglement essentially or at least an
effective size of entanglement to solve
a problem
of size x right you know at the time i
think our keys were 512 bits long
you know they were like three qubits or
something at the time
okay that's a long damn way from being
able to break a 512
bit key i just looked it up this morning
the minimum
specified key length for digital
certificates now is 2048 bits
and so essentially this rsa encryption
algorithm
is in a race adding more bits to stay
ahead
of the increasing power of quantum
computing
so talk a little bit about how the power
of quantum computing
is related to the number of qubits that
are simultaneously entangled and
let's start with that and then we'll go
on to the other pieces that sort of
delineate the effective power of a
quantum computer
absolutely jim yeah so a nice way of
thinking about this
i mean this is the power of information
in general the amazing power of
information is that a small number of
bits
can have a very large number of possible
states so
you know if i have one bit it can be
either zero or one
you don't have to call it zero one it's
conventionally called it could be yes or
no or true or false or head through
tails it's just a question of having two
states
and then two bits well there's zero zero
zero one one zero one one so it's got
four states and then three bits you've
got zero zero zero zero zero one zero
one zero
oh i'm getting tired of it they've got
eight states right
four bits have 16 states five bits of 32
states
ten bits of a thousand twenty fourth
dates
twenty bits have more than a million
states thirty bits have more than a
billion states
forty bits have more than a trillion
states so the number of states grows
very rapidly
with the number of bits it grows
exponentially if i have
n bits the number goes as 2 to the n and
that number gets very big very fast so
for instance
300 bits well 2 to the 300 is around 10
to the 90.
10 to the 90 power is the number of
elementary particles in the universe
so with 300 bits you have enough bits to
label
every elementary particle in the
universe if you could figure out a way
where to put the label so
so the this is the power of classical
information was tremendously powerful
because it shows you have you have the
potential to explore
a huge information space even with a
relatively small number of bits
and the power of quantum computation
means oh
if i have quantum bits and they can be
in superposition
and entangled with each other then i can
explore that same
huge space simultaneously so with 300
cubits i can explore a space where
if i were going to do this classically
on a classical computer my classical
computer
would have to be the size of the whole
universe
so it these the the size grows very
rapidly
of course being able to control those
bits
and build a quantum computer that's
harder
so the back in 1993 before shore's
algorithm
i made the first technologically
feasible design for quantum computer
prior to that the first quantum
computers were proposed by the idea was
proposed by paul benioff around 1980
picked up by the famous noble lord
richard feynman in the early
80s and then david deutsch kind of
codified the theory of quantum
computation in the mid-80s
but all that time nobody had any idea
how you could build a quantum computer
there's some
quote from feynman at some conference he
says i'm going to talk to you about this
notion of quantum computation now you
may think i'm
crazy and nobody has any idea how to
build these things but i'm going to talk
about it anyway
so back in the late 1980s early 1990s i
said
you know i wonder how you might build
one of these things and i started
working on how the physics of building
quantum computation
early 1990s i learned about what's
called electromagnetic resonance which
is what happens when you zap
atoms with lasers or when you zap spins
with microwaves
and i realized you know you zap atoms
with lasers in the right way
you could build a quantum computer so i
i published a paper in science called a
technologically feasible quantum
computer
that was 1993 and in 1994 i started
working with
folks to start making the first quantum
logic gates and the first quantum
computers
and so it worked very well except the
computers the quantum computers only had
a couple of quantum bits
we started with two cubic quantum
computer turns out you can actually
demonstrate
you know a do a proof of principle
demonstration of quantum computation
with only two qubits which
we did the first algorithms with those
then we went to three qubits oh now you
have eight states that's great
then we went to four qubits and five
qubits then you know eventually
by the early 2000s we were up to like a
dozen or two qubits
and then about you shows you the
progress is slow
because you're trying to convince
atoms molecules superconducting systems
to process information at the most
fundamental possible level
it's simply hard to do and so the
progress is slow
but then about five or six years ago
hartmut nevin at google
convinced sergey brin it's like hey say
you know if we were to invest a hundred
million dollars or a couple of hundred
million dollars and actually
building a quantum computer we could do
it the technology is there
and they hired john martinez from
university of santa barbara
and they went wild and they immediately
started building quantum computers that
had you know
you know 20 cubits 30 cubits 40 qubits
and then ibm and microsoft who had been
you know working on quantum computing
for decades and
to kind of like you know at a smaller
level they say hey google's eating our
lunch we got to do this too
so they invested 100 million dollars and
they started building much larger
quantum computers and then places like
you know intel and huawei said
we don't even know what a quantum
computer is but we better invest in this
too
anyway so last five years things have
been going kind of crazy in the field
but the net result is that now people
have quantum computers with
you know on the order 50 to 100 quantum
bits they're still not big enough to
factor large numbers and break public
key crypto systems
thereby instilling fear in the heart of
agencies with three letters in their
name
like nfo not that such agencies have
hearts
but anyway that they but so they still
are not there in terms of breaking the
public key crypto systems
but you know it's starting to look like
it's within shouting distance of doing
so
why has it been hard you know why do you
have to spend hundreds of millions of
dollars to get 100 bits to talk to each
other
jesus that doesn't sound too hard but
obviously it is
so what makes that a hard problem it's
useful to remember what happened when
people
first started building you know
conventional electronic digital
computers
they were they first started with vacuum
tubes and then they started with
transistors
and then the computers that you had to
put together you had to wire together a
huge number of vacuum tubes or a huge
number of transistors each
vacuum tube where each transistor
corresponded to a single switch or a bit
and the vacuum tubes would break and
blow out and then you know
some bit in your computer has blown out
where is it how do we find it
and so to build a a conventional
classical computer with a few hundred or
a few thousand bits also took
an apparatus the size of the room an
effort by a huge expensive effort on the
part of the government
and years and years to build so it's
hard because you're you're trying with
competition it's hard you're trying to
build
a system with many different parts that
functions reliably
and you can control each of the parts
that just isn't easy
it was already hard to do back in the
1950s and early 60s in terms of vacuum
tubes and transistors
and now we're trying to do this at the
level of individual atoms
the change in conventional classical
computing came with the invention of
integrated circuits
in the late 60s early 70s where it
became clear oh
look we can actually have a systematic
way of putting lots and lots and lots
and lots of transistors on a single
semiconductor chip and then we can
figure out ways to scale it up
and to make more and more and more and
while we're maintaining things
in a reliable functioning state
so with quantum computers the place
we're at right now
is more like the place where classical
computers were back in the
vacuum cube era of the 1950s early 1960s
where we're just trying to figure out
the basics of how we put together the
different qubits
how we make them talk with each other in
a way where they can do so accurately
and come up with schemes for scaling up
and so
it's just simply hard to do it was hard
to do with classical computers as well
and it's a lot harder if the things
you're putting together or individual
atoms
you have to address each atom
individually you have to make them talk
with each other
pair by pair you have to zap them with
lasers to try to tickle them and
convince them to
to process information the right way
it's not you know not an easy thing to
do and it's taking a long time
moreover it's not even clear even though
you know huge progress has been made in
the last five years about this
it's not even clear we're going to get
there because just in the same way when
we had vacuum tube computers it's like
ah this is never going to work you know
vacuum tubes are we have a computer once
we have you know
10 000 or 100 000 vacuum tubes they're
always going to be blowing out it's
never going to make we can never make
this happen
so we're still at the stage where we're
aspiring to make them bigger
if we can make them bigger that'd be
great i mean not just for
for you know it's fine to to factor
large numbers break publicly
cryptosystems and thereby screw up the
whole
business of the world which is to buy
extra crap on the internet
how disruptive would that be but but
there's lots of other great
applications for quantum computers as
well and those would be wonderful if we
could
achieve them and it looks right now that
what we they might actually do within
our grasp
interesting in addition to the number of
qubits which is what we usually hear
about in the popular press
you know i had a concept quantum
computational
density which i don't know that's a word
that you all actually use but i use it
myself
and i include the number of qubits plus
how long you can keep the
entangled qubits from deco hearing and
the error rates
and the sort of three together provide a
combination which talks about
the actual amount of work you can get
done you know how do those other two
parts the decoherence times and the
error rates
factor in the equation of how useful
quantum computation could actually be
you're right on target there jim those
are very important you can't actually
think of how to build a quantum computer
with actually looking at this
three-dimensional space rather than a
one-dimensional space of
how many qubits you have how long can
you keep them coherent which
in the quantum mechanical cases how long
can you keep this kind of
wave coherent coherence of the different
waves making up the different states of
the qubits
because once they become incoherent you
have a cubit that's like
zero that's zero and one at the same
time in this funky quantum mechanical
way it's cool
because it's coherent but when it loses
its coherence then it just
lapses into something much more
classical which is being either zero
or one which you can get just
classically
so there's the coherence time which is
how long you can maintain this
superposed wave-like nature of entangled
qubits
and then finally there's the error rate
which you can think of
is when you're flipping qubits from one
state to another
how accurately you can do that so right
now the numbers are kind of like
well we have 50 to 100 cubits and
um the coherence times uh for
superconducting qubits are in the order
of one ten thousandths of a second 100
microseconds 100 millionths of a second
and during that time you can put in on
the order of
10 000 individual qubit operations or
or q bit flips and the error rate so
that
the precision which which they can be
done is currently around
99.7 that's the
that's kind of the world record right
now for for the accuracy of an
individual cupid so
three parts out of a thousand
sounds pretty accurate but it turns out
that if you actually really want to do
something like factor a large number
you're going to need something like 100
000 qubits
you're going to be able to do millions
of operations
and to do this you're going to need
error rates that are kind of
one part and 10 000 99.99
rather than 99.7 percent or sorry
accuracy that's not the error rate so
the error rate is one minus the accuracy
if you like
um so there uh we're still a ways away
you know we're still a few orders of
magnitude away
in terms of being able to have the right
number of quantum bits
being able to do have the coherence
times are now very good
they will stay coherent for a long time
those are actually quite adequate at the
moment we don't really need longer
coherence times
but um though of course it'd always be
nice but more bits
and and better accuracy so lower lower
error rate
and the great thing about that is that
you know we we have a goal
we can attain it it's great and moreover
it's in sight
you know making a we really basically
need a factor of 10
in terms of the precision for doing the
the logic operations well you know
that actually is quite doable if we've
already gone up by a factor you know we
started out
at 50 times less accurate than we are
right now we can get another factor of
10 we're good
number of qubits okay we need to go up
by a factor
of 100 but we're up by a factor of 100
already from you know the early days of
quantum computing too
so you know maybe we'll get there uh
very hard to predict these things the
technological prediction is a mugs game
and in some areas some areas it's not
maybe obviously moore's law
has been not so bad for quite a while
and
i suppose the rate must have an
exponential associated with it with
respect to
improving computational density in the
quantum world as well
of course the question always is is
there a wall we know there's a wall on
moore's law one wonders where there is a
wall or not
in the quantum world yeah so it's
interesting you should mention moore's
law because you know which is
as you know but i'll just say it again
is the this
empirical fact you know an observation
about technology made by gordon moore
the head of intel back in the 70s it's
like oh look
the number of bits in our computers has
been growing by a factor of two
every two years and at that time was
also the case that the speed of the
computers was growing by a factor of two
the clock rate was going by factor of
two
and so the overall computational power
of the classical computers was growing
by a factor of two or so
every couple of years it's important to
remember about moore's laws that moore's
law
is it's not a law of nature it's uh
empirical law about technological
progress
and it's actually continued for an
amazing period of time i mean it's
really started
back when people first started building
computers in the late you know mid to
late 1940s
and has gone on ever since for 70 years
which is why our computers are extremely
powerful by now
but moore's law if you actually look at
its different features none of its
individual pieces some of them are
exponential like the density
of bits in transistorized wafers has
been going up by a factor of two every
two years
but the speed the clock speed of the
computers
stopped doubling just right after 2000
and the reason was very simple it's like
it was doubling every couple of years it
was doubling
they're getting faster and faster and
then starting around 2003 or something
like that when the clock speed got up to
a few billion times a second a few
gigahertz
it's like you start pushing it further
than that and the chip started melting
and that's something it's hard to get
around so it's have stayed at
a few gigahertz a few billion times a
second ever since so
not all aspects of computation
continue to proceed by a factor of two
every two years
and in quantum computing it actually
hasn't really happened that way
in the sense that you know the number
of of quantum bits that we have has not
doubled
every two years it's been a slower pace
uh which i think comes from the fact
that we're really starting at the very
bottom scale and trying to put them
together
with in moore's law it was really an
observation but what happens is when
you've got a good platform
the silicon wafer and the etched chip
and then you proceed by making the
materials more pure
by making the etching more precise by
allowing you to pack more transistors on
the chip
by process of miniaturization in the
case of quantum computers we actually
started
off at the most miniature scale already
and then we're trying to put together
more and more quantum bit per qubits
it's a different kind of process
and it hasn't been obeying moore's law
though
as i said it's sped up a lot quite
recently which shows that if you invest
but you give money to smart people who
know what they're doing and invest in a
good program for building better quantum
computers by god you're going to get
better quantum computers
yeah that's cool we'll come back to the
different architectures that people are
working on but before we do that let's
talk a little bit about
some of the applications and algorithms
and sort of
higher level approaches to quantum
computing
first what we've been talking about and
i believe it's the field that you're
active in
one can divide quantum computing roughly
into
digital quantum computing now what i
call the quantum circuits guys and i
put you in that bucket but there's also
some analog
approaches to quantum computing like
quantum annealing or adiabatic quantum
computing
could you talk a little bit about the
distinction between those two
yeah and do you mind if i talk a little
bit about
about you know quantum analog computing
in the sense
the original sense of the word of analog
computing
or the original sense of the word analog
computing is
you build a physical system like an
electronic system
and you program it so that it's dynamics
is an analog
of the dynamics of some system you'd
like to simulate may i talk about that
as well
sure good i think i'll talk about that
first because i think that that's
important it was really the first
suggested application of quantum
computers so back
uh paul as i mentioned paul benioff
first proposed quantum computers
back in 1980 and in 1982 richard feynman
said you know a good application
of these quantum devices would be to
simulate other quantum systems
and he said wouldn't it be nice if we
had a box
with knobs on it and the thing inside
the box was quantum mechanical
and when we turned the knobs we were
changing the dynamics of the quantum
thing
inside the box and if we turned the
knobs to the right setting we would
program
this quantum dynamics in the box to be
an analog
of the dynamics of something we want to
simulate for example
we might want to simulate strong
interactions
in elementary particle physics or we
might want to simulate
quantum gravity and what happens inside
a black hole
or we might want to simulate what
happens to electrons as they hop around
inside a semiconductor all these are
very quantum mechanical kinds of
processes
they're very hard to simulate on a
classical computer
because the classical computer has to
follow all these different waves that
are wiggling around in superposition and
there are a lot of these waves
so it's hard to simulate these quantum
systems on a classical computer
so feynman said hey wouldn't it be great
to have
a quantum simulator that could actually
simulate these other systems
and he was basically proposing the
quantum version of an analog
computer so how do we make a quantum
system where we can program that
to be the analog of other quantum
systems and this is a very
widespread application certainly for you
know someone like me who has a phd in
physics
it's like and doesn't understand how
quantum systems are behaving it would be
awesome to have a quantum analog
computer a quantum simulator that you
could use
to say now i wonder why this
superconducting system is not behaving
the way it should let's try another
design let's see what happens let's
simulate it let's see what happens if we
do it this way
that would be awesome so that's a great
application
and that is one of the applications that
in fact is
for quantum computers that's the most
practical right now pretty much as soon
as quantum computers began to be built
you know remember i proposed the first
design in 93
ignacio sorak and peter zoller proposed
how to build quantum computers using
iron traps
in 94. i started working with hans moya
and delft
to do superconducting quantum computers
in 96 and 97 first superconducting
quantum computers
were 1999 yasunov nakamura
shenzhe nec so these technologies have
been developing one of the very first
applications is this is this quantum
simulation
uh back in 94 i looked at its original
finding paper and said
you know that's a great idea now that we
have quantum computers that are being
built
how do we do this so i started writing
algorithms for quantum simulation
analog quantum computers and pretty soon
i convinced david corey at mit to start
implementing these
and now these are one of the primary
applications that people use for for
quantum computers
uh one of the most exciting ones is to
use it for figuring out chemical
structure
and drug discovery uh these are
wonderful applications for even quite
small
quantum computers and that's taking the
kind of
quantum nature of a system that's
processing information
and as you were saying before you're
just kind of writing
the rules for how this quantum system
behaves so that
it behaves like another system that you
want it to behave like
and and this is a great application for
quantum computation
and then you mentioned several other
applications for quantum computers
that are not you know the digital kind
of quantum computation where
the paradigm or the most famous example
digital quantum computation is short
algorithm and factoring as we were
talking about before
so um i i call this uh you know
quantum systems being quantum so
and and you know being quantum is easy
for a quantum system but it's very hard
for a classical system to figure out
like you or me
or classical computers to figure out
what it means for a quantum system to be
quantum and how it's behaving this way
so there's what's called adiabatic
quantum computing where you have a
quantum system where
it always remains in its lowest energy
state it's so-called ground state
but you slowly change the parameters of
the system so it oozes over into a new
ground state
new lowest energy state and at the end
of this kind of slow
process of changing that's what
adiabatic means it basically means
moving so slowly you always remain in
the ground state at the end of the slow
process of changing you've changed the
parameters of your system so that the
final state of the system
encodes the answer to some hard problem
that you couldn't find in any other way
that's a very cool use of quantum
computers and there's a
company d-wave that's been making these
adiabatic quantum computers now for 15
years
and that's a great application of
quantum computation
and then there's a whole host of other
applications including the use of things
like light
and continuous variables things that
wiggle up and down in continuous ways
like the states of light interactions of
light
with atoms and matter to try to make
systems
that can uh compute and solve problems
that you couldn't do otherwise
in fact there's the one of the reasons
why
building large-scale aquatic computers
is not so easy
is that quantum systems give you
a huge set of possible opportunities
in ways to construct novel quantum
devices and have them process
it process information in novel ways
and the fact that they have give you
great opportunities
makes it hard to take advantage of any
one of them
so i guess how would you say with great
quantum opportunity become comes great
quantum responsibility yeah and we'll
talk about that just a few minutes the
different technologies
say there's many of them you mentioned
quantum simulation for chemistry
that's trying to put together an effort
to use quantum simulation to find a
better way to create
ammonia you know we think ammonia what
the hell you know but ammonia is the
main basis for fertilizer and it's a
huge
like 50 billion dollar a year industry
you can make it even 10 more efficient
and be a gigantic win
so those are you know some of the kinds
of things that i'm hearing about
out in the hinterlands one more
algorithm i'd like to
ask about is the hhl algorithm
and in fact what does the l stand for
about lloyd you were involved with that
right could you tell us a little bit
about quantum machine learning
sure i mean hhl let me mention aaron
harrow or navidad in hastadine
who are the two h's there i called the
holy hell algorithm because hhl was like
it's easy to pronounce for that so so
short proposed this algorithm for
factoring back in 1994
and it was already clear he used this
feature that
that you could use a quantum computer to
extract the periodicity you know how
fast a wave is
wiggling up and down this is what's
called the quantum fourier transform the
fourier transform as you know is a
classical technique for extracting
periodicities
and then alexa tayev came up with a
variant on shore's algorithm around 1996
and that was kind of all for quite a
while in fact the progress in building
quantum computers slow though it is
has been much more steady than the
progress in coming up with algorithms
and applications and remember
that quantum computing works by taking
these waves
and superposing them on each other
adding up these waves
and around the mid 2000s
when again you know not many algorithms
quantum algorithms had come up
i had the idea of looking at let's look
at
kind of a much broader class of
procedures than what people have been
looking at
so far so the idea if you look at the
mathematics of how you take these waves
and add them up
the waves can be thought as what are
called vectors and a vector is just a
big long list of numbers
for a wave you can say oh let's like
take the wave and let's like discretize
it in space and each number tells you
the amplitude of the wave at a click
replace like
the first number is oh the wave is zero
the amplitude is zero then the next one
is one oh look the
wave is one the next one is two oh look
the next one is two
the next one is two again oh look it's
leveling off the next one is one oh look
it's going back down
the next one is zero oh look it's back
down at zero so you see the wave we can
encode the wave as just a list of
numbers
and the advantage of quantum computation
here is that list of numbers can be
extremely
long remember with 300 qubits 300
quantum bits the list of numbers
is 2 to the 300 the list is you know as
long as the total number
of elementary particles in the universe
so the advantage of quantum computers
is that these vectors these you know
digitized version of waves
can be huge and then the
the study of how these vectors operate
these long list of numbers is what's
called linear algebra
and the way you add that you can add
vectors together that's just you know
quantum superposition in the case of the
quantum systems
and another thing you can do vectors you
can multiply them with by what's called
a matrix which is
just a even bigger list of numbers now
in the form of for instance
a square rather than just a long list
so linear algebra is basically the study
of how you take these lists of numbers
and how you manipulate them by
multiplying them and adding them with
other lists of numbers
and a lot of what classical computers do
is just this linear algebra
and a lot of for instance when i teach
my undergraduate mechanical engineers
about
numerical methods the things you need to
know for you know doing calculus or
building bridges or programming
computers to do design
to understand you know the material
properties of structures
a huge amount of what they're doing is
just taking these classical computers
programming in big big lists of numbers
and then multiplying
and adding and dividing them just doing
these linear algebraic techniques
so it's a big part of both pure math and
a very large part of kind of practical
and applied math
with linear algebra so i had the idea
it's like hey you know
these quantum computers why do quantum
computers do a good job
it's because quantum systems are
basically doing linear algebra
you know the state of a quantum system
is a huge long list of numbers
we don't have direct access to the
numbers in this list but the state
they're there
and when the state gets transformed you
know when a quantum system evolves from
one state to another
these numbers change and the way they're
changed is by multiplying these numbers
by a big
matrix you know another big square array
of numbers
so the quantum systems the reason why
quantum computers are better than
classical computers for some problems is
that
quantum systems are hardwired to do
linear algebra
so i had the idea of saying well you
know let's look at just some other
linear algebraic techniques let's see
what we can do
and one very common problem in linear
algebra
is you have a set of equations
in unknown variables and you want to
know
what the answer is and meaning this is
out like like
2 x equals 6.
what is x right well
okay in this case x is equal to 3.
so and then you have here's another one
in
more variables x plus y
equals seven x minus y
is equal to two well i just made that up
in my head because
i knew the answer because i put it in
it's oh x is equal to three
and y is equal to one right that's our
old
simultaneous equations from you know
algebra one in eighth grade
right exactly exactly and so um
you know we have systematic ways of
doing solving these equations
actually these systematic ways it's
often called it's often called
gaussian elimination it's named after
carl friedrich gauss
and the reason it's called that is was
actually invented in the west by isaac
newton
but somehow gauss made some improvements
so they called it after gauss
and then it was invented in china like
1500 years ago or longer so it's been
around for a long time
and the systematic way of doing this
everybody who went through eighth grade
into this knows it's like okay
first we add together these equations or
subtract them from each other after
multiplying from each other to eliminate
certain variables
until we end up with the answer oh look
it turns out y equals one
and then we plug y equals one back into
the rest of the equations and we find oh
look x is equal to three
right and so uh that's called gaussian
elimination
and it takes some time and if you have
more variables it takes a longer time
and actually time it takes grows rather
rapidly with a number of variables
so i started looking at this problem
like i wonder if we could you know
if the numbers we're looking for are the
entries in a vector
the vector is a quantum state it's just
a list of numbers
and we can write these linear equations
by saying
oh let's take this list of unknown
values
we multiply them by a vector that gives
the kind of like
2x plus y is equal to 2x plus y
part or the you know x minus y part that
you can get by multiplying this list of
number unknowns by
a matrix and then you say oh and it's
equal to a known vector that gives us
2x plus y is equal to 7 x minus y is
equal to 2.
so then we have this list of the knowns
then we
we are rephrasing the problem in the
form of
ax equals b where x is an
unknown vector b is a known vector and a
is a known matrix so
i said let's see if we can solve that i
said you know what
i know how to solve that it's pretty
funny actually the way we came up with
the solution so
avinalton
and i just made them a big italian lunch
and the rule of coming out and working
with me there is that you spend the
whole day you work really intensely for
like four hours i make
a large and delicious detail well i i
regard as delicious they may not but a
large italian lodge
you eat it while you're eating you talk
about other things you don't talk about
physics
but while you're washing up afterwards
you're allowed to start talking about
physics again
we were washing up after the lunch and
and aaron said well so seth
are you have any problems you're working
on i said yes i am actually
working on this problem you know uh
ax equals b and we want to find
x is equal to the a inverse multiplied
by
b and i said i can do 99
of this problem because i can show i can
solve the problem with the form
of you know i can say i can produce e
to the a inverse x where this is just
some you know
different version the same problem i
said but i can't get to the last step
and aaron said
oh but that's easy and he explained how
you do it and that was it
that's a wonderful story about
collaboration exactly and then of course
of course then it took three months
actually to get the paper written to
figure out all the
dot the i's across the t's and all the
epsilon deltas
but then we had the answer to that and i
think that that
i mean first of all it's a fun problem
because it solves a very fundamental
question
in linear algebra that i think is great
but i think the other thing that was
really fun about that work
is it showed it kind of said it was that
it's not just like they're just a few
problems in linear algebra that we can
solve like this original one from like
finding periodicities from schwarz
algorithm it's like
oh look we can we can solve equations
with a whole bunch of unknowns
and then a bunch of us realized you know
oh this means that pretty much all of
linear algebra which is a huge field
right pretty much all of that would be
much much much faster on a quantum
computer if we could build one
which leads me to my next question when
i read about hhl i said
linear algebra what else is based on
linear algebra
deep neural nets has anyone to your
knowledge
attempted to at least design the
algorithms for what
neural nets might look like on a quantum
computer
absolutely and that's that's exactly
what we decided to look at
um was just so neural networks are you
know
a classical method for trying to
figure out you know simulate on a
computer in a
stylized fashion what happens inside the
brain and famously they're used
in very widespread fashion now
artificial neural networks are used for
machine learning for finding patterns
and data
because it turns out if you make huge
honking artificial neural networks and
tune them
turn them loose on gigantic training
sets of dana
that they do pretty well at least you
know for extremely important societal
problems like
recognizing pictures of kittens on the
internet
which actually you know i was a little
surprised that that when when google
was amazing that google was able to
train a deep neural network
to recognize that there are lots of
pictures of kittens on the internet to
figure out how to do it but
you know it's not that strange because
if you pick a random picture from the
internet and show it to computer the
chances
are that it's a kitten they're already
relatively high so just guessing
yeah it's kittens probably going to
probably do pretty well
um yeah so this is a great question jim
and and that in fact is one of the
primary proposed applications of quantum
computers right now
is quantum machine learning in general
and things like quantum versions of
neural networks in particular
and i think here's is there's a
tremendous opportunities
because we have these fantastic classic
machine learning
algorithms now you know it's no secret
that over the last
five to ten years that classical machine
learning has been going wild and
accomplishing things that were
very unexpected uh whereas previously
actually for the previous 20
or 30 years it hadn't been working that
well to tell the truth
somehow this threshold got crossed where
the amounts of data got big enough
the computers got more powerful and the
methods were defined to the point where
they could really do some pretty
impressive things
um you know not just you know uh beating
the world go
champion and go or recognizing you know
doing facial recognition or pattern
recognition or voice recognition it's
kind of a lot of things are coming
together um that doesn't mean i'm still
going to be willing to just get into a
car
that's driven by some big machine
learning algorithm and have it drive me
around at 70 miles an hour through the
streets
but there's still some glitches to be
worked out
yeah but the quantum version of this is
remarkable as well
and i think that that it suggests going
forward
um one thing that we're working a lot in
my group is kind of a partnership
between
quantum methods and and the classical
methods because as you say
classical neural networks the way that
they work is
you take a huge vector a huge long list
of numbers you multiply it by a gigantic
matrix called a weight matrix
and then you take the resulting vector
that you get after you know transforming
this vector
in this fashion using linear algebra and
then you apply some kind of nonlinear
transformation on it
this nonlinear transformation is the
analog the
the computational analog to what a
neuron does
the neuron has all these synapses with
signals coming in
those signals get processed in a way
where they get combined and added and
subtracted from each other
in a way which is like this multiplying
these signals these list of numbers by a
matrix
and then the nonlinear part is okay do i
fire or not
the neurons question is like oh well
yeah the if the inputs
process inputs get above a particular
threshold by gum i'm gonna fire
if they're not i'm gonna hold my keep my
powder dry i'm not gonna fire
so the nonlinear part is this firing
part and the neurons the linear part is
this
combining of a huge number of incoming
messages
so for the quantum version of neural
networks
a really great application of quantum
mechanics is like oh look the quantum
systems are great at combining vast
numbers of these signals encoded as
quantum states
you know adding and subtracting them
multiplying them by different numbers
and putting them together
let's take those and let's combine them
with a classical device that's going to
take
the results you know of say classical
measurements made on these states
and then do these non-linear
transformations
and this this kind of hybrid
architecture uh
it's one of the nice things about it is
you know it's going to be at least as
powerful as either the quantum or the
classical on its own because
you know you could always just turn the
classical part entirely off and have a
fully quantum device or turn the quantum
part entirely off and have a fully
classical device
but by getting them to collaborate with
each other the quantum the classical you
have a device
that is at least as powerful as just
classical or just quantum on its own
that's a very exciting set of
applications
yeah it looks like an area that's going
to be well worth following
doing that let's now turn to something
that our investor
listeners which we have some would be
interested in which is
the underlying technical substrates
for implementing quantum computing two
of the big ones
that seem to be still hanging in there
is the two leading contenders are
super conductors and trapped ions i
think you talk a little bit about those
two and then we'll talk about some of
the others
yeah that's a very it's a very good
question about i mean i'm sure and i'm
sure there's a lot of question right now
it's like
there's a race to build the first
scalable quantum computer who will win
you know the you know the state of the
known universe hangs in the balance
um that kind of thing and uh
so yeah the i mean i think the first
thing to recognize
about how you build a quantum computer
is that
you know pretty much any quantum
mechanical system
makes a good makes it could be a quantum
bit because the whole quantum in quantum
mechanics tells you
that there's this kind of discrete
nature this kind of digital nature to
quantum mechanics at bottom
so recall you know when i made this
first design you know back in 1993 for
how you might build a quantum computer
uh i scraped around for years like for
five years or so trying to figure out
how to do this because
there was no technological guidance
nobody knew how to do it and then
finally i said hold but hold it you know
really any quantum system will work we
can have an atom we've got an electron
electron you know
over here that's zero electron there's
one
we have the spin of the electron
electron spinning clockwise we call that
zero electrons electron spinning
counterclockwise we call that one
it doesn't have to be electron it can be
a proton or a neutron with its spin
clockwise counterclockwise zero one
we could have a photon which is a
particle of light
where it's it's polarization you know
wiggling back and forth
is zero wiggling up and down as one and
that is the advantage that it moves from
one place to another the speed of light
which is kind of
useful if you want to communicate
quantum information from one place to
another
every atom has internal atomic states
and these eternal
atomic states can be can be controlled
and changed by zapping them
with light any two atoms that
interact with each other their
interaction can be taken to
perform a quantum logic operation
and then actually so and this of course
is the basis for iron trap quantum
computing
that was proposed by ignacio serach and
peters older in 1994
it's like oh yeah look you can take or
maybe it was 1995 i forget
it was a little after shore's algorithm
they said look you can take these ions
which are
atoms where an electron has been
stripped off as in the old joke
you know two hydrogen atoms
stagger out of a bar and one says oh
shoot i lost an electron and the other
one says are you sure
and the first one says yeah i'm positive
sorry ha ha
that's terrible that's a groaner of the
first water
anyway you strip electrons off the off
the atoms they're now ions
they're positively charged so they repel
each other
and then you trap them in a trap that
has
has both static and dynamic
electromagnetic fields and you can line
them up in a trap
they interact with each other because
they repel each other because of their
positive charge
and the they have internal states that
can store quantum information for a very
long period of time they make extra
excellent quantum bits or qubits and
then you can take their interactions
effective direction act
interacting and then by you know
tickling them in the right way you can
really get these interactions to allow
them to perform you know quantum logic
operations on several quantum bits at
once it's very nice
very nice substrate for design for
making a quantum computer
the atoms are extremely coherent they
have very long coherence times
on the order of hours right
and so coherence is not a problem the
laser techniques for zapping the atoms
with lasers for getting them to talk
with each other
that actually those are very well
developed and so you have very high
accuracy gates with very low error rates
and they're really the main problem is
just from the technical limitation of
putting
ions together in iron traps once you've
got about 100 ions and a single iron
traps that's about all you're going to
get into one iron trap
otherwise there are too many that start
all apart so then you have the problem
of
if you want to build a scalable quantum
computer to make it larger and larger
you have to put
more and more and more ions together and
indeed you need a way of having
different iron traps talk with each
other
and this is currently the technologies
we're doing that are kind of slow
processes of quantum communication that
take quite a while
to move quantum bits from one iron trap
to another that i would say
is probably the biggest bottleneck at
the moment making large-scale
uh computers using iron traps because
the other features are great the
coherence is amazing
impeccable basically eternity so far as
we're concerned we're not worried about
quantum coherence
and the ion traps the coherence times
our coherence time is very long
the the control parameters in terms of
the
the performing low error rate gates that
still has a lot of work to do
you know there remember the kind of like
benchmark you really want to get is
99.99
accuracy before performing individual
gates
there's still a nine or two away from
that they've got a factor of 10 or more
for doing that but that's in good shape
there the bottleneck has this
communication
but this is a great technology for
decades it would because of the long
coherent specific control
characteristics this iron traps were
considered to be the front-running
technology for
building quantum computers ever since
they were proposed by
sorak and zola and then implemented and
this is one of the features for which
weiner got his nobel prize
in physics so that's a great technology
one of the two
front-running technologies then so that
was early 90s or like 94-95
or mid-90s a bunch of people started
talking about the possibility of using
superconducting systems
for performing quantum computation as i
mentioned my introduction introduction
from this came from talking with hans
moay
m-o-o-i-j hard name to pronounce a very
distinguished professor
of uh of physics at the uh
technical university of delft kind of
the mit of delft
except in holland they believe it's
better than my team so anyway i'm not
sure i believe that but it's great place
and hans had the idea that you could use
something what's called macroscopic
quantum coherence that had been talked
about a lot by um
people like tony leggett who got his
nobel prize for
elucidating how superconductivity work
so the idea here
is and other people by the way like as i
said
nakamura were working on the same id at
the same time so the idea
of macroscopic quantum coherence is the
following
so a superconductor is a state of matter
typically something like
a metal like aluminum and when you cool
it down below
a certain temperature you find
mysteriously and quite remarkably
is that the resistance of for the flow
of current goes to zero
this is because below a certain point
and in order to get resistance
you need the thermal expectations of the
system to
be sufficiently great that will knock
the electrons out of the state that
they're in in order to get resistance
but there's just not enough energy in
the thermal fluctuations to do that
so the electrons once they start going
they just keep on going forever and so
you can build a loop a superconducting
loop
where one of the states of the loop is
electrons going around the loop forever
in a counterclockwise direction
and another state of the loop is
electrons going around the loop forever
in a clockwise direction these are
perfectly reasonable states of a
superconducting system
now if you have macroscopic quantum
coherence
then what happens is this macroscopic
state of the electrons you know we've
talked but we're talking a state of
trillions of electrons here
trillions of electrons going around the
loop clockwise forever
or trillions of electrons going around
the counterclockwise forever
you can create a quantum state which is
trillions of electrons going around the
root the loop
in a clockwise direction and in a
counterclockwise direction
at the same time just in the same way
you can have a single electron that's
over here and over there at the same
time in some funky quantum mechanical
sense
that nobody understands so this
macroscopic quantum coherence is really
weird because it's like wow trillion
electrons going
clockwise around the loop and going
counterclockwise around
at the same time just doesn't make sense
and it doesn't make sense but that's the
way it is
and in the late 1990s nakamura shenzhai
at nec
and subsequently hans moy kasper van
deval a delft an experiment that i was
honored to be able to participate in in
helping with the theory
managed to demonstrate this macroscopic
quantum coherence and showed the
existence of the first superducting
cubits so it was 1999-2000
an amazing wonderful
demonstration brilliant experiments
and the only issue for using these for
quantum computing is that the qubits
sucked that's a technical by the way ah
yeah
that's the acronym s-u-c-k right
exactly you know you could get these
super currents going in this quantum
super position
and they go around the loop you know a
few hundred times and that was it then
the whole thing would fall apart they'd
decode here
you know the coherence times were very
short we had no idea why this was going
on
a whole bunch of people tried to make
them better a little bit of progress
happened
some practice and design happen and you
know we said oh let's make them smaller
you know let's try different techniques
for etching out the superconducting
circuit
let's you know bring out all the
possible you know methods we have for
doing it
and then around oh i don't know mid
mid-2000s maybe 2007 2008
rob shulkoff who was at yale then said
you know what
let's try making the qubits bigger
instead of smaller and
let's take these superconducting qubits
you know
they're part of a superconducting
circuit that has these different
features in them and like we have a lot
of flexibility in how we design these
things let's try making them bigger
and you know what this worked like a
charm turned out that making them
you know ten times as big which inside
and you know spatial extent which made
them a hundred to a thousand times a bit
big in terms of the amount of material
that was in them
this meant that they became much more
coherent and there was amazing insight
by rob
and his group there including people
like michelle defray
which was that oh what's what's the
problem the problem is
in these you know in the metals and the
insulators that make up these
superconducting
qubits even though these are very very
refined and we're doing the best we can
there are these little tiny defects in
places
that are out of our control and these
defects are what are causing
this decoherence and causing things to
be messed up
now if you make the system bigger
you think oh but you know now you have
more defects
and that's true but what also happens is
that the electrons
that are doing the superconductivity
their waves
get spread out over a much larger volume
and so each the electron experiences
each defect to a much smaller degree
and when you do a little bit of the math
you find out okay
you know the effect of each defect goes
something like okay
the number of defects grows linearly
with the volume
or the size but the effect of the
electron goes down as something like one
over you know the cube of the size or
something like that or the square of the
size depending on the
on the particular architecture and
geometry and so what happens is the
coherence time just shoots up
and along with this this innovation
along with other innovations we're going
and other other kind of superconducting
systems
the coherence times of these
superconducting circuits went from being
100 nanoseconds you know a tenth of a
millionth of a second
down to 100 microseconds or 100 two
thousand microseconds it went up by a
factor of 10 to the four of a thousand
to ten thousand even a hundred thousand
over the course of around a decade
or less and that meant that all of a
sudden these superconducting qubits
which
previously had been limited by their
coherence times that was no longer the
limitation
an amazing wonderful technological
advance
and the thing about superconducting
qubits is because you can etch them
on chips with technologies that are
similar to those
where you etch semiconductor chips so
here you're etching things like you know
aluminum
and aluminum oxide onto the chips along
with other kinds of you know
transistorized controls
you have a lot more flexibility for how
you put the qubits together than you you
do when you have ion tracks
so now we have these two technologies
and the ones that that
that google when google when harper
nevin had this insight hey you know we
can do this we can wrap this
up he said let's go with the
superconducting technology
the time is right for that we can build
larger superconducting technology
chips and he listed john martinez at the
same time john martinez had this strong
vision for how to make this happen
and they did and they made it happen and
uh very impressive so the devices are
remarkable
buying traps haven't gone away there's
an amazing startup done by chris monroe
called inq
there's a lot of academic research on
this where inq they also have you know
100 cubits in their system
and then they're actually the thing is
because of what i described before it's
like
any quantum system is a reasonable
candidate for doing quantum computation
you know i our conducting systems are
the current front-runners in the
technologies
but coming up behind them are a lot of
other technologies which have all kinds
of potential advantages
and are not yet as well developed as the
superconnecting systems and ion traps
merely because
they haven't had as much investment for
them in them and these include things
like
other atom and optical technologies
all optical technologies companies like
xanadu
or uh jeremy o'brien's company
sorry jeremy i forget the name of your
company right now but it's a great
company
new company using uh uh atoms and optics
using entangled in different ways so
there are a lot of other technologies
that are
currently in the form of things like
startups that might very well have
breakthroughs and leap to the front of
the pack
it's a little too early to decide in my
opinion at any rate to decide it's just
going to be superintendent systems it's
just going to be iron traps
or one of these other technologies
because they all have their advantages
now what i stumbled across and i was
doing my research for the show
has the mouthful name non-abelian
india ah apparently that's microsoft's
bet
uh what's that oh yeah this is a
wonderful i mean
this non-abelian anions as the name
suggests are like
i have no idea what the hell they are
but it sounds super cool
exactly that was my reaction what the
i think i know what
none means but i'm not sure what abelian
ineons might be
right yeah this is a very beautiful
theoretical idea that was proposed
by the the brilliant scientist electric
type back in the 1990s
and he was using what are called
topological effects
topological effects are things like you
know topology are things like based on
knock theory
right a knot is something what is a not
well a nod is an arrangement of strings
where you take a rope or a string and
you you interweave it with each other in
a particular way
and once it's interwoven in a particular
way the actual
kind of like exact way that the string
is lying on top of each other
doesn't really matter what matter is is
how it's interwoven
and so if i tighten it up it's still the
same knot or i loosen it a little bit
it's still the same knot
the knottedness comes with the topology
of how it's knotted together
and ketaya came up with this amazing
idea that
there are these topological excitations
at microscopic levels you have these
systems where
the way the system behave depends on its
topology kind of the way it's
knotted together rather than on the
exact microscopic configuration of the
system you know exactly where
the the the electron is and so
there are these things called these
topological excitations of the feature
that how they behave and what they do
depends on how
you knock them together and the way you
knock them together
is actually you kind of move them around
each other
i pick up one system and then i i i
take it in a circuit like it takes a
little version to move
all the way around another system and
the way this is described if you do it
in time if you imagine unraveling this
in time
it's like a braid i have you know the
time the history of one system is a
string
here's one system that's sitting still
it's just like a string that's pulled
tight
and then the history of the other system
that i'm moving around it's like another
string
but i take the string and i take the
front of the string
and i move it all the way around the
other system so i'm braiding the history
of this system around the other system
does that make sense it's hard this
would be easier if i
i had some props with me yeah it's hard
to get one's head around
but it's interesting that it's
essentially quantum manipulation of
topologies holy
right so it's you you just by by taking
system and moving one system around the
other then that's a kind of if you if
you unravel this in time it looks like a
braid where a braid is you just have a
series of ropes or strands of hair
you pick up one strand and then you
braid it around the other system
properties of the dynamics of the system
end up being a property that's braiding
and so the the topological part
is is the braiding part and then
the fact that what happens to the
there's a kind of a trivial way of
braiding which is called abelian
braiding whereas if you
if you do it to one system then you to
another system doesn't matter what order
you do the braiding in and that is not
enough doing quantum computation
the non-abelian part says what happens
to the quantum systems depend on the
order in which you braid
one around another and then the anion
just means that you can do anything you
want with these cis with these
topological systems including doing
quantum computation
so the non-quantum computation with
non-abelian anions comes from this
braiding of these topological quantum
systems around each other
i know it's like i'm trying to i'm just
doing my best gem i'm just doing
my best i i can't can do no more okay
let's hop
up to how does it do on our three
factors
number of qubits decoherence time and
error rates
so great so that's the what is what is
good about
these these these topological systems
it's the fact that the way they behave
is insensitive to just kind of the
microscopic state of the system
remember in a knot i can have a knot
that's where the the it's knottedness
and then the form that the knot takes
doesn't matter just like how tightly the
strings are pulled or not it doesn't
matter you know i take
you know i have a loose knot and i move
a little bit of string to one place
through another i poke around and the
knot it's still the same knot
even if i move everything around i like
pick it up and i shake it
yeah that's topology right but apology
is that
the what it's doing is insensitive to
you know the details of the geometry
right so the great thing about these
topological computational methods
and this was pointed out by kataya from
the 1990s is
that the computation that they're
performing is insensitive to the exact
way that you braid things around each
other
you know you're a little sloppy about
how you braid the things around
who cares what happens in terms of the
computation is exactly the same
so the great thing about this from a
theoretical perspective is these
topological methods of computation
which are the ones being pursued by
microsoft are intrinsically insensitive
to how you do this
so they've got an intrinsic error
correction built in
already whereas in a kind of a more if i
may call it conventional quantum
computer like an ion trap or a
superconducting system
you have to perfectly encode the error
correcting in by building a whole bunch
more qubits by doing a whole bunch more
error correcting operations and it's a
mess
so that's the real advantage of these
topological methods
and this was as you mentioned this is a
method that that so
there they have the kind of error rate
if you can make it happen
then you're in great shape and microsoft
a long time ago decided back in the late
90s
due to the brilliance of michael
friedman who said
who there's a fields medalist you know
the mathematical equivalent the nobel
prize except even more
more prestigious feels medalist in all
things topology
he said look back in the 80s he was
already saying look babe we could use
these topological methods with quantum
systems to do computation
and then in the late 90s he started
station q at microsoft back in santa
barbara it's like let's make this happen
and microsoft's been working on it ever
since a beautiful set of ideas wonderful
experiments
with these topological excitations which
you know previously didn't exist they
now actually exist
uh the problem is they exist at the
level of you know
one qubit and they haven't yet been able
to do a single two-qubit
operation so for the theory side it's
fantastic from the basic
physics side it's amazing the
experiments done by people like you know
charlie marcus or leo von kavenhoven at
delft they're beautiful
wonderful experiments kind of nobel
prize character kind of experiments
but in terms of building quantum
computers the number of qubits is very
small in fact they still don't really
have two qubits to rub
together that's not much so then on our
three-part model they're
good on decoherence they're good on
error rates but they can't
so far figure out how to even entangle
two cubits
well yeah so that's a problem now it's
possible they may have some some
breakthrough in this but you know
turns out that this particular method
maybe because it's so
beautiful and fancy and accomplishes all
these other things you know you don't
get something for nothing so
by having this kind of comp these
topological methods
you have to struggle so hard to get
these beautiful uh you know
resilient topological quantum
excitations that
the rest of the features like scaling it
up then you take a big hit
in that yeah no free lunch right
now let's move on to let's jump out of
the fairly straightforward world of
quantum computing
into the wild blue yonder late in your
book actually
it's in the beginning too and here and
there but especially late in your book
you start making some strong arguments
about the universe as a quantum computer
and some amazing claims about how
thinking about the universe as a quantum
computer
solves some minor little problems like
quantum gravity
right which is the biggest question in
physics today
you know how the hell do we reconcile
the macro sphere and general relativity
with quantum mechanics
so why don't you go on a wrap here for a
couple of a few minutes
on the universe's quantum computer and
what that insight provides us in terms
of trying to figure out
how the universe is well jim well this
is a
this yeah this is a story that i've been
very important for me personally
because the question of quantum
information and quantum gravity is how i
got into the field in the first place in
1983-84 i was taking
i was a graduate student in cambridge on
a marshall scholarship doing this
masters in philosophy of science and and
i took stephen hawking's uh graduate
seminar on quantum gravity
at that time and said you know this
stuff that i'm doing about information
and quantum mechanics can really fit in
well with this quantum gravity stuff and
i started working on it ever since i've
been working on it ever since not very
successfully
may i say and actually nobody else was
doing this for a long time
and now just suddenly all of a sudden
the last few years everybody's decided
that quantum information and quantum
gravity goes together so
that's nice but in terms of the universe
as a quantum computer
the argument there it's not even an
argument and
i know it sounds you know like
completely overblown like oh the
universe is a big quantum computer it's
like
oh when you study quantum computation
everything's a quantum computer it's
like when you've got a hammer everything
looks like a nail
but it's not really that that's not
what's going on here it's really has to
it's related to what i was describing
earlier about how you build quantum
computers
so in figuring out how to build chronic
computers in the first place i was like
i wonder what kind of would be a good
like you know substrate for building
quantum computer and that was like
huh you know could be anything because
everything out there
in the universe you know every atom
every elementary particle every electron
every quark every photon
carries with it quantum information and
when
different atoms electrons photons quarks
interact with each other
that information is changed and
transformed
and so the carrying information you know
registering information in a quantum
mechanical fashion
every individual piece of the universe
does that
and then when two pieces of the universe
interact with each other your two
elementary particles bounce off of each
other
that information that they carry is
processed and transformed
so when we build a quantum computer all
we're doing is just accepting the
reality that everything out there in the
universe is already
registering quantum information and
processing it in a systematic fashion
so to build a quantum computer what we
need to do is kind of hack into this
ongoing computation
and see if we can't you know by tickling
things with lasers or mazers or you know
or like by electric potentials and stuff
if we can't kind of guide this ongoing
computation towards directions to doing
things that we'd like to do like quantum
stimulation or factoring
so my realization that the universe was
really the whole thing was a quantum
computer
really came from this very practical
engineering challenge
like hey how do we build a quantum
computer what can we use oh we can use
anything we want because they're already
processing information in a quantum
mechanical fashion these electrons are
already
effectively computing and what we need
to do is not you know
make them compute or exploit them to
make them compute
we need to recognize that they're
already computing and processing
information
and then intervene into this this
computation they're already performing
to program them
to do something different and something
we'd like them to do hence the title of
my book programming
the universe you know when we were
building a quantum computer
we're not actually you know doing
something that the universe wasn't doing
already
we're simply intervening in part of the
universe to program it to perform
a complication we'd like it to perform
and if you ask
electrons and atoms and through chronic
interpretation the right way very nicely
speaking their own language
tickle them with light in the right
fashion by gum they're going to do that
for you and that's what's happening with
quantum computation
so when you actually think of the
universe as a as a quantum computer i
actually would say it's not you know a
metaphor it's just a fact
right it every piece of the universe is
registered information
you know when pieces of the universe are
direct they're processing information
information processing is computation
that what computation is by definition
and the universe is processing
information and computing in a quantum
mechanical fashion it's just a fact it's
not a metaphor
but some of the implications that you
take from that are quite astounding
well i mean you know you take this facts
and i'm going to just call it a fact
because it's a fact
and you say well what are the
implications for this well one you know
implication you said as well maybe we
could understand this
famous unsolved hundred-year-old
unsolved question about how you make a
quantum theory of gravity
using ideas from quantum information
processing that would be great
you know i've been working on this since
early 80s
and you know making progress slow
and not even steady slipping backwards
and more recently people like
lenny suskin you know the last few years
have advocated doing this
um and now there are a lot of people
working on this problem maybe we'll make
progress
quantum mechanics and gravity is a more
than 100 year old question
and indeed a few years ago at the at the
100th anniversary
of einstein's discovery of the theory of
general relativity
some friends of mine and i who do we all
do quantum gravity we said
let's have a conference entitled a
hundred years of
failing to quantize gravity
[Laughter]
because let's face it we still don't
know how to do it
and if someone tells you you know they
know how to do it it just merely means
that they're a string theorists
but i think that there's actually you
know so it could be helpful for that
that would be great
i think there's one aspect of the fact
that the universe is
in fact a big quantum computer that is
really amazing and there's an
implication
of that that is remarkable and does
explain something
that is very beautiful and profound
about the universe
which is why the universe is so complex
ah i was going to ask you that was going
to be my next topic let's just roll with
that
this will be our last topic and then we
will wrap up
good so let's just move into that
because this is a very wonderful
question
and people have been asking this
question as look for as long as they've
been people you know
you stare up at the night sky what's
going on out there
what what are all these stars you look
at the world around you know you know
what is all
are all these living things my god look
at human beings what the heck is going
on here
it's totally out of control with
complexity
where did that come from a very
mysterious
question that's very hard to answer and
you know in some sense
is this question is that the basis for
organized religion
disorganized religion personal religion
etc
and you know people in science have been
scientists have been trying to answer
this question
for hundreds of years as well also
failing to do so
actually from the point of view of
physics it's particularly mysterious
because
one of the features of physics is when
you look at things at their most
fundamental level they look simple
you know the standard model for
elementary particles
fits on a t-shirt it's simple
how do you have these simple laws and
get all this complex stuff
coming out of it well the fact that the
universe is performing a quantum
computation
actually provides an explanation for
this because a computer at bottom
is in fact a simple thing the dynamics
of a computer
oh it's a simple the computer it's got
information in it stored in bits
and the quantum computer is stored in
quantum bits or qubits that's fine
bit is a very simple thing it's
something that has two possible states
which we just happen to call zero and
one
or electron here an electron there and
then the the elementary logical
operations out of which the computations
are built
are also very simple it's like oh we
just flipped the bit we move the
electron from here to there or
you know we have a we flip this bit if
this other bit is one
oh we only flipped the bit at the other
bit as one that's called controlled not
non-operation
it's a very simple logical operation and
if you look at the most complicated
computations you know
that involve bajillions of bits a
technical term
and performing gajillions of logical
operations that's also a technical term
all it is is a lot of bits and flipping
these bits in a systematic fashion
well that's a computation and out of a
computation
even though the actual dynamics and
underlying physical reality of the
computation is simple
just bits bits interacting with each
other bits flipping in a systematic way
you can get very very very very
complicated behavior out of a
complication
so this is great because this tells us
how we can get
a universe that has very simple laws
simple ways of representing information
simple quantum mechanical rules for
flipping bits
and yet and it can start from a very
simple state at the time of the big bang
and yet it can spontaneously generate
any kind of complicated behavior that
you
would like to think about and for this
we just need a little extra bit of
mathematics and the mathematics is very
simple it says
we take something that's capable of
computation
we give it a random program so we give
it random bits to start out with
and we look to see what happens and
there's a beautiful aspect
of mathematics called algorithmic
complexity
theory that says this computer
programmed at random
is going to has a finite chance of
producing any complex system you can
imagine
not only anyone that already exists but
any complex system that can exist
and anyone that you can even imagine and
that's a very beautiful piece of math
and when we apply to the universe as a
whole we say look
the universe is a quantum computer it
gets programmed at random by these kind
of just like
quantum randomness but when we take a
computer we give it a random program
what do we expect happens
we expect amazing beautiful wonderful
complex things to happen and that's what
happened
yeah so that the quantum randomness or
pseudo-randomness or whatever it is
was the mechanism by which complexity
was bootstrapped from
a relatively uniform early universe
is that it in a nutshell exactly i mean
and there's lots of very cool stuff in
this it's like it's like it has to do
with gravity and actually quantum
gravity it's like
oh you know the universe was very
uniform to begin with and at a state of
maximum entropy how did it get
so non-uniform turns out when you have
gravity
that uniformity is bad clumpiness is
good
matter likes to clump together to form
things like you know stars and planets
and galaxies
and then once things start to clump it's
like oh
you know actually then this
spontaneously generates the information
theoretic conditions that allow
computation to bootstrap itself into
more ever more complicated forms by
generating ever more complicated forms
and patterns in energy so called free
energy so you know
first you get planets stars galaxies you
get
then you get you know on planets you get
more and more complicated chemical
compounds that can recombine in ever
more
complicated chemical fashions to perform
more and more complicated chemicals that
oh my god
then a certain point it's like oh this
group of chemicals could be rna or
something like that
they figured out a way to reproduce
their state but with variation
once you have things that reproduce with
variation then that's just life
man you know and and then life is off
and running and so there's a very
natural tendency at each stage along the
game
for the information processing power of
the previous generation if you like
to get bootstrapped into an ever more
complicated form of information
processing in the next generation
though it is difficult to maintain that
right the famous error catastrophe and
evolution
right it's not easy to maintain that
complexity from
generation to generation that's what's
so interesting about life
i had an amazing conversation with
stuart kaufman once out of sfi for about
four hours and we both ended up at the
same point which was how the
did pre-organic life
managed to get over the error
catastrophe because the rna world
alone the error rate is too high but
when you get to the dna plus all the
replication machinery the error rate is
low enough to defeat the error
catastrophe
how the hell did we get over that bridge
without the air correction
and we both said if we know that it
may actually have something to do with
the fermi paradox just maybe some
goddamn art maybe it only happened once
but anyway i would put that caveat
on your story which is yes quantum
randomness creates
complexity but often the complexity
breaks down again very quickly
absolutely and in fact the one of the
features that exactly be the same
instability that makes you know matter
and energy clump together to form stars
and galaxies and then
you need instability in order to go from
something that's
homogeneous and uniform to something
that's non-homogeneous and non-uniform
the same you know instability that says
oh simple groups of chemicals together
are not unstable to the formation of
more complex groups of chemicals
and then oh just complex groups of
chemicals are unstable to
the set of auto catalytic sets and say
something like the rna world if that's
how
the world came together but then the rna
world is unstable
to things that have dna and error
correction that can be more meticulous
and create even more complex forms
so i don't claim to understand this but
you know something like that definitely
happened
interesting well i think we're going to
wrap it up here we have covered some
amazing amount of ground
and people who hung with us to the end
have gone on an amazing
journey so i want to thank you very much
seth for
just a tremendous episode thank you so
much jim next time
fermi paradox indeed
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern